A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1801-1957
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1801-1957
Library of Virginia
23881, 24808
596.33 cubic feet (1343 boxes, 490 volumes on shelf, 7 oversize boxes, 6 oversize map case drawers, and one rolled oversize tube); Box numbers 1-1337
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
These materials are available on microfilm and should be served instead of the originals:
Series I: Copies of deeds, etc., c. 1812-1925, Misc. reel 2562.
Series I: Corporate holdings, 1866, Misc. reel 2562.
Series I: Minute books, 1837-1947, Misc. reel 2642.
Series II: Notes and bills payable and receivable, 1856-1864, Misc. reel 2699.
Series III: Foundry record of guns cast, 1861-1865, Misc. reel 2689.
Series III: Guns tested for the US, 1857-1858, Misc. reel 2689.
Series III: Payroll ledger, 1863 Aug. - 1864 Aug., Misc. reel 543.
Series VII: Correspondence, Outgoing: 1861 May-August (Box 886); 1861 August-December (Box 886); 1864 August-December (Box 889); 1864 December-1865 February (Box 890); 1871 June-October (Box 914); and 1875 May-June (Box 949) have been photocopied and bound. Serve bound photocopy instead of originals.
Acquisition Information
This collection came to the Library of Virginia in five accessions. The bulk of the collection came from the Tredegar Company as two accessions: Gift of the Tredegar Company, Richmond, Virginia, October 1952 (Accession 23881), and Gift of the Albemarle Papers Manufacturing Company (successors to Tredegar), Richmond, Virginia, 1958 (Accession 24808). THESE TWO ACCESSIONS, 23881 and 24808, ARE USED TO DESCRIBE AND IDENTIFY THE ENTIRE COLLECTION, WHICH ALSO INCLUDES 22989, 24297, AND 24809.
At later dates other intergral Tredegar records were donated to the Library of Virginia and are interfiled within the larger collection.
Stock transfer account book, 1837-1849. Transferred to the library from the office of Dr. H.J. Eckenrode, Director of History, Department of Conservation, 1949 (Accession 22989).
Minute book, 1867-1899, photostat copy of original in custody of Tredegar Company, 1955 March (Accession 24297).
Drawing of a rifled field gun, photoprint. Lent for duplication by Charles H. Robertson, Albemarle Papers Manufacturing Company, Richmond, Virginia, 1958 April (Accession 24809). The drawing is filed with the oversize collection, folder 92. (See Appendix A for a complete listing of oversize materials).
Although not interfiled within the collection listed below are related company records located in the Business records collection:
Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1845-1865 (Accession 25744).
Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1845-1864 (Accession 26393).
Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1857-1935 (Accession 26601).
Tredegar Iron Works Minutes, 1876- 1879 (Accession 33052).
Biographical/Historical Information
The following is a brief outline of Tredegar's 120-year history. The history of Tredegar pre-Civil War to 1880 has been the subject of several publications, which should be consulted for more in-depth presentations: Kathleen Bruce, Virginia iron manufacture in the slave era. (New York: A.M. Kelley, 1968); Charles B. Dew, Ironmaker to the Confederacy: Joseph R. Anderson and the Tredegar Iron Works. (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1966); and Dennis Maher Hallerman, The Tredegar Iron Works: 1865-1876. (Thesis: University of Richmond, 1978). Another publication which includes a detailed analysis of the Tredegar site and structures, including its water power system is: Michael S. Raber, Patrick M. Malone, and Robert B. Gordon: Historical and Archaeological Assessment, Tredegar Iron Works Site, Richmond Virginia. September, 1992. (LVA Accession # 40407)
The Tredegar Iron Company was organized in 1836 by Francis B. Deane, Jr., an experienced Virginia blast furnace operator, and a group of Richmond businessmen, interested in expanding the local market for railroad iron. The company was chartered in 1837 and the following year acquired the Virginia Foundry Company. The earliest products were, for the most part, railroad construction, including axles, wheels, and gears. By 1841 though, the company was incurring great debts and the investors moved to reorganize the firms management. The most significant change made was the naming of Joseph R. Anderson (1813-1892), as the companys new agent.
In 1842, Deane resigned as superintendent and John Tanner was hired as his replacement. The company, through Anderson, soon secured U.S. Navy contracts for chain cable, shot, and shell. In 1843, Anderson leased the property for five years and worked on expanding the market into ordnance and railroad sales, producing angle iron, axles, rails, and shells. In 1848 Anderson purchased the Tredegar property and did business in his own name, Joseph R. Anderson and Company. The foundry operations were enlarged and a cotton factory on the land was converted to a spike factory. The high cost of transporting goods to Northern markets and competition from the British iron industry led Anderson to expand into the Southern market. Anderson also entered into a number of partnerships to manage the rolling mill and an enlarged locomotive operation. The locomotive partnership, begun with John Souther, led to the 1852 construction of a new boiler works and a finishing shop. Under a new partnership, Matthew Delaney managed the machine shop and locomotive operations. His son, Alexander Delaney revived locomotive sales with better designs and Tredegar became the largest antebellum Southern locomotive maker. Anderson also leased land on the site to Lewis D. Crenshaw for a new flour milling operation, and to A.J. Bowers and Asa Snyder for a stove works. Tredegar also owned several coal mines and blast furnaces, including Cloverdale, Grace, Catawba, and Rebecca in Botetourt County; the Australia in Allegheny County; and Mt. Torry in Augusta County, Virginia.
By the beginning of the Civil War, Tredegar was the largest ironworks in the Confederacy, with almost 700 black and white workers. The ironworks was virtually the sole source of heavy guns, projectiles, gun carriages, plates for iron-clad vessels, wheels and axles for railroad rolling stock, furnace machinery, and a variety of other products for Confederate munitions factories and navy yards. Although heavily damaged during the evacuation fire in April 1865, Tredegar made a swift transition back to peacetime production. The company was reorganized in 1867 as a new corporation, the Tredegar Company, whose assets were the Tredegar works, including the Armory rolling mill. Joseph R. Anderson and Company continued to hold interests in the remaining furnace properties.
In 1868 Tredegar received a major contract to supply the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad with rails and bridgework for the entire line. A national sales office in New York City was established, with John Tanner dispatched to run it, and a network of agents were positioned across the country. Foundry, rolling mill, blacksmith, carpenter, and boiler shop facilities were expanded by 1869, and a new puddling mill was erected. The rail rolling facilities were upgraded and new chair mills, spike machines, and horseshoe machines were introduced. The company made some non-railroad products, including engines, boilers, cast-iron pipes, nails, marine plates, bar and angle iron, decorative iron building fronts, and structural bridge iron. By 1873 Tredegar had more than twice its prewar capacity and employment that exceeded its highest antebellum totals. During this period the company supplied iron bridges, rails, and thousands of kegs of spike which were used to rebuild southern railroads. The company survived the panic of 1873 but was forced into receivership in 1876 when several northern railroads with which it had contracts and agreements were forced into bankruptcy.
As iron gave way to steel in the 1870s and 1880s, Tredegar found it did not have the capital necessary to make the production conversion. The companys financial footings had been rebuilt by the 1890s but the works then produced for a local market. Tredegar continued to make iron products, producing ammunition for the Spanish American War, World War I, and World War II. Spikes, horseshoes, rail fastenings, and car wheels were constant sellers, and led to expanded facilities for their production. The period between the two world wars was one of low profits, although the rail fastenings continued to be the primary market products.
In 1957 the company sold its Richmond plant to the Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company, and moved some of its rolling mill equipment to Chesterfield County, where operations persisted until 1986. In 1987 the rolling mill was sold to Cleveland Track Material in Cleveland, Ohio. The Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company, in 1962, purchased the Ethyl Corporation, including the name, and so in turn, the Tredegar property in Richmond became Ethyl Corporation property. In 1973 Ethyl Corporation paid for the restoration of the gun foundry and its chimney.
The Valentine Museum/Richmond History Center established a museum at the site of the ironworks in 1992. The Valentine Riverside Museum restored the outdoor machinery and structures, as well as the Pattern Building, Office Building and Carpenters shop. Unfortunately the museum was not a success and closed on 4 September 1995. In 2003 the Tredegar National Civil War Center was created to operate a museum at the site. Plans are underway to add an interpretive center by 2007 and a library, research center, and offices by 2010.
BIOGRAPHIES
Archer Anderson (1838-1918), eldest of twelve children of Joseph Reid Anderson and Sally Eliza Archer Anderson, was born at Old Point Comfort, Virginia. He served with the 21st Virginia Infantry, Company F, 1st Brigade, Aquia District, and as chief of staff to General Joseph E. Johnston during the Civil War. On 9 August 1859 he married Mary Anne Mason, daughter of John Young Mason, U.S. minister to France. They had seven children including, Archer Anderson, Jr., J.R.J. Anderson, and St. George Mason Anderson. He was president of Tredegar Iron Works from 1892 to 1918. He died 4 January 1918 and was buried at Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Archer Anderson, Jr. (1866-1942), third of seven children of Archer Anderson and Mary Anne Mason Anderson, was born in Richmond, Virginia. He graduated from the University of Virginia with a masters of arts and practiced law in Virginia. Upon his fathers death in 1918, he became president of Tredegar Iron Works. He died 30 January 1942 and was buried at Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Joseph Reid Anderson (1813-1892), was the youngest of nine children of William and Anna Thomas Anderson of Botetourt County, Virginia. He graduated West Point in 1836 and worked as an engineer in Virginia. He married Sally Archer in 1837, daughter of Dr. Robert and Frances Williamson Archer. By 1841, he had acquired an interest in the Tredegar Iron Works in Richmond, which supplied iron products to railroads and the U.S. government, and he became owner of the company in 1848. When the South seceded, Anderson offered his services to the Confederate Government as an infantry officer and was commissioned a brigadier-general in September 1861, serving in North Carolina and Virginia. After being wounded at the battle of Frazier's Farm in 1862, Anderson resigned in mid-July to return to Tredegar Iron Works where his talent was needed more than on the battlefield. The company operated throughout the war, but after the surrender of Richmond, the U.S. government confiscated Tredegar Iron Works. Upon Anderson's request to President Johnson for a pardon in the fall of 1865, the Works were returned to him. Anderson continued to head Tredegar Iron Works and remained active in state, city, and local affairs until his death in 1892.
Edward Richard Archer (1834-1918), son of Robert Archer and Mary Silvester Wormington Archer, was born in Old Point Comfort, Virginia. He served with the Confederate Navy during the Civil War. After the war he became the chief engineer at Tredegar Iron Works and held that position until his death on 13 March 1918. He never married and was buried at Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
Robert Archer (1794-1877), oldest of four children of Edward R. Archer and his second wife, Mary Silvester Wormington Archer, was born in Norfolk, Virginia. He became a physician and in 1813 enlisted in a local artillery company and was commissioned as a lieutenant and surgeons mate. He spent the next twenty-five years as an army physician, stationed at Fort Monroe, Virginia, and, for a short while, at Fort King, Florida. On 28 March 1816 he married Frances Williamson in Norfolk, Virginia. They had five sons and seven daughters. In 1839 Archer retired from the army and took up farming near Fort Monroe. In January 1848 Joseph Reid Anderson, Archers son-in-law and head of Tredegar Iron Company, persuaded Archer to move to Richmond to become superintendent of the Armory Iron Company. By May 1848 Archer had risen to presidency of the company. In 1859 the Armory mill and Tredegar works merged into the newly formed Joseph R. Anderson and Company. While Anderson served in the army during the first year of the Civil War, Archer and John F. Tanner ran the company. After the war Robert Archer and his son Robert Samuel Archer both sat on the board of directors of Tredegar Company. Robert Archer died 19 May 1877 in Richmond, Virginia, and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Presidents of Tredegar: 1843-1892 Joseph Reid Anderson, 1892-1918 Archer Anderson, 1918-1942 Archer Anderson, Jr., 1942-1947 Paul E. Miller, and 1948-1957 Raymond W. Krise
Scope and Content
The Tredegar Company Records are housed in 1345 boxes, 490 volumes on shelf, 7 oversize boxes, 6 oversize map case drawers, and one rolled tube. The collection is arranged into eight (8) series. Series have been designated for: I. Administrative records; II. General Accounts; III. Production and Labor records; IV. Purchase and Receiving records; V. Sales and Shipping records; VI. Correspondence: Incoming; VII. Correspondence: Outgoing; and VIII. Anderson family papers. These records include balance books, cashbooks, contract books, correspondence, daybooks, estate accounts, family papers, insurance policies, invoices, journals, ledgers, minute books, patents, payroll ledgers, real estate files, sales books, stock certificates, suit papers, tax returns, vouchers, and war department contracts. The records document the history of one of the most important and largest iron making factories in Virginia and the Confederacy.
Following is a brief overview and some highlights of the collection. A more in-depth description of the collection can be found in the Series and Sub-series level description. It is recommended that the researcher read the Series level scope and content notes thoroughly before accessing the collection.
The finances and sales of Tredegar products are well documented in the records and included are daybooks, ledgers, and salesbooks from the earliest days of the company (Series II and Series V). The records include an almost complete run of payroll ledgers, 1852-1957, and are a good source for researchers interested in labor and wages (Series III). The correspondence series include an immense amount of materials, over 980 boxes and 171 volumes on shelf, and a large date range, 1841 to 1957 (Series VI and VII). These two series provide a wealth of information on the types of materials Tredegar produced throughout its history, as well as the types of raw materials that it purchased. Included are letters from companies, including banks, ordnance departments, railroads, and shipping companies, from across the country, although mainly the southeastern states.
Of note to the Civil War historian, the collection includes records relating to the production of munitions, the C.S.S. Virginia, slave labor, and the role of Tredegar during the war. Included are cashbooks, correspondence, daybooks, ledgers, minutes, reminiscences, and sales books from the Civil War era. In regards to munitions, also of note are the correspondence, drawings, receipts, sales books, and war department contracts. Tredegar manufactured munitions for every major conflict including the Civil War, Spanish-American War, World War I, and World War II.
For researchers interested in the use of slave labor, there are some noteworthy records. A volume titled, Copies of letters, etc., contains information on the use of slave labor (Series I); A volume entitled, Notes and bills payable and receivable, 1856-1859, contains lists of slaves who worked at Tredegars blast furnaces (Series II); Payroll ledgers, note the race of workers, free or slave (Series III); Contract books contain contracts with slave owners and list slaves hired (Series V); and also included are bills of sale for slaves purchased (Series VIII, Subseries 1). Researchers should also study the minute books and correspondence series for additional information.
Unfortunately there are few, if any, internal memoranda regarding employees and there are not any files on employees and employee-managerial relationships in the collection. The outgoing correspondence occasionally contains letters regarding employees, changes in wage levels, or accidents at the mill, but these are not prevalent and require in-depth research to uncover (Series VII). The production and labor series contain the most information on employees, and these records relate more to wages and production levels (Series III).
Of note are the numerous agreements and deeds that can be found in the collection. A number of agreements and deeds can be found in Series I: Administrate records, Real Estate files, and also in Series VIII: Anderson family papers, Subseries 6: Estate of Joseph R. Anderson. The deeds may duplicate one another but researchers should check both series for all pertinent information. A complete listing of all agreements and deeds can be found in Appendix B at the end of the finding aid.
Tredegar maintained one of the most extensive waterpower systems in the country to supply power for its factories. In 1933 Tredegar became involved in a lawsuit with Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, which owned the James River and Kanawha Canal, over the rights to the water supply. Papers, including correspondence, depositions, drawings, exhibits, and reporters transcripts, relating to this lawsuit can be found in Series I: Administrative records. Researchers should also check, Michael S. Raber, Patrick M. Malone, and Robert B. Gordon: Historical and Archaeological Assessment, Tredegar Iron Works Site, Richmond Virginia. September, 1992. (LVA Accession # 40407), for additional information on the water system.
Around 1952-1958, when the collection first arrived at the Library of Virginia, an itemized container listing was prepared by a staff member. The collection was organized into Administrative records, General accounts, Purchasing and receiving records, Production and labor records, Sales and shipping records, Correspondence, and Anderson family papers. When the archivist undertook to process the collection in 2001, it was decided that these groupings would remain. It is unknown if that was how the papers originally came to the Library of Virginia, but since 50 years had passed since they arrived at the library, it was decided that these groupings were the most logical. The original finding aid incorporated some type of Arabic and Roman numbering system which was eliminated, as it was deemed unnecessary. A key to the old finding aid is available in Appendix C at the end of this finding aid for researchers looking for materials that were linked to the old numbering system.
Whenever size permitted, volumes were housed in boxes for better protection. Volumes that are placed directly on the shelves are interfiled with the boxes, following the order of the container listing. General materials were arranged to the front of each series.
Oversize items are filed in 7 boxes, 6 map case drawers, and one rolled tube. There are a total of 93 oversize folders, containing about 1,000 drawings. These include drawings of angle plates, axles, cast iron posts, chairs, fish plates, gears, horse shoes, joint bars, land, munitions, rails, and wheels, c. 1880-1957. Of note is a drawing of an iron rifled field gun, 1861. Oversize items, which were part of a regular sized filing unit, were removed from their respective folders. In their place, removal notices list the item(s) separated and the oversize folder number to which they have been removed. For location and content list of oversize folders see Appendix A. (Boxes 1227-1233)
Several items of the collection were in need of restoration, which was performed by Etherington Conservation Center, either in the in-house lab, or in the North Carolina main office. The conservation work consisted mainly of repairs of broken, torn, and glued pages, damaged bindings, the cleaning and unbinding of moldy volumes, and the preparation of custom boxes to house fragile volumes and those without bindings.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
SERIES I: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS (1801-1957) (bulk 1870-1957)
The Administrative records are housed in 56 archival boxes and 14 volumes on shelf and arranged alphabetically by folder title, with general materials arranged to the front. This series consists of Albemarle and Tredegar merger data, corporate holdings, copies of deeds and agreements relating to the company, insurance policies, inventories, minutes, patents, real estate files, reports, stock files, suit papers, tax returns, and wage adjustment papers.
The general materials include a circular issued by the company in 1867; copies of Tredegar bylaws, 1871; history of Tredegar by Joseph R. Anderson, 1890; wage adjustment papers concerning the salaries of employees and officers during World War II; codes of fair competition issued by the National Recovery Administration, 1934-1936; photograph of Tredegar iron workers, c. 1910; report on a fire at the horseshoe department, 1926; and a resolution by the Richmond Chamber of Commerce commemorating the death of Joseph R. Anderson, 1892.
The two volumes entitled, Copies of deeds, agreements, etc., and, Copies of letters, clippings, etc. involving the company, include a wide variety of papers relating to the history of Tredegar. These volumes were created by Archer Anderson Jr. and they include documents which he felt related to the history of the company. The volume, Copies of deeds, agreements, etc., includes copies of deeds relating to the land surrounding Tredegar and the Grace and Rebecca Furnaces in Botetourt County, Virginia. Many of the original deeds may be found in this series under, Real Estate Files. Also included are letters relating to the Kanawha canal, Tredegar Street, and the death of Joseph R. Anderson in 1892; copies of the original act of incorporation of Tredegar in 1866; and copies of the notes on the survey of Rebecca Tract, 1907.